Guide to the Mason Crum papers, 1885-1974 UA.29.02.0032
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mason Crum papers
1885-1974
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Crum, Mason, b. 1887
UA.29.02.0032
11 Linear Feet
Mason Crum (1887-1980) served on the faculty in the Department of Religion at Duke University from 1930 to 1957, specializing in race relations and Christianity, as well as the social history of the Gullah community of the South Carolina Sea Islands. The papers contain correspondence, printed material, writings, clippings, slides, photographs, negatives, and glass slides, and and a sound recording. Subjects of interest include religious aspects of race relations and segregation, African American religion and churches, Gullah dialect and culture, Methodist Episcopal Church, South, and the Lake Junaluska, N.C. retreat. Photographs are of the Sea Islands, Lake Junaluska, Mason Crum's family, former slave Charles Baxter, and images relating to the Washington Duke family and Durham.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
Nitrate negatives are closed to use; copies are available. Please contact the Rubenstein Library Research Services staff for assistance.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Mason Crum papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1973-1977.
Biographical Note
Educator, author, Methodist minister; born Frederick Mason Crum; A.B. Wofford College, 1909; Ph.D., University of South Carolina, 1925; LI.D, 1950. Professor of Biblical Literature, Duke University, 1930-1957. Author, Gullah: Negro Life in the Carolina Sea Islands (1940); The Negro in the Methodist Church (1950). Married (1914) Katherine Howell of Waterboro, S.C.; six children.
Mason Crum was born in Rowesville, S.C., the son of William C. and Nonie (Neeley) Crum. His father was a merchant, farmer, and landowner in Orangeburg County. Crum received his undergraduate education at Wofford College, Spartanburg, graduating in 1909. He then attended the School of Religion at Vanderbilt in 1910, and was principal of a school in Fort Mill, S.C. for a year. In 1911, desiring to work for a Ph.D. in order to teach at the college level, he entered Harvard for courses in psychology and philosophy. After a year's study, he returned to South Carolina and began what his autobiography calls a kind of detour in life. During the few next years, he worked as an agent for the Department of Agriculture, sold cars, and became interested in the ministry. He was ordained in the Methodist Church in 1919 and received a pastorate in Summerville, S.C. in 1920. Still desiring to teach, he was appointed Professor of Religious Education at Columbia College. From 1920 to 1930 he taught courses in Biblical literature, psychology, ethics, and education, and completed the Ph.D. program in education at the University of South Carolina, receiving the degree in 1925; his dissertation was on the Project Principle in Religious Education. He was a member and officer of the Chi Phi fraternity.
He began teaching Biblical Literature part-time at Duke University in 1930, and was appointed to the faculty two years later. While at Duke, Crum worked extensively on the question of race relations and Christianity and began studying the social history of the South Carolina Sea Islands, and especially the Gullah communities on Edisto and St. Helena. He took part in cooperative efforts in bettering race relations through education, and was active in a number of organizations. He began teaching a course in Black History, The Negro in the Religious Life of America, in 1954; the course was described as an examination of Christian churches' attempts to apply the Christian ethic to race relations, although Crum intended it as a course about Black life and culture. Crum retired from Duke in 1957, and, after moving to Florida, he volunteered his services as a pastoral counselor to a clinic associated with the Presbyterian Church of Hollywood, Florida. He and his wife returned to North Carolina sometime after 1963, and took up residence at Lake Junaluska, the Methodist Church's retreat in western North Carolina, where Crum died in September, 1980.
Collection Overview
The Mason Crum papers include correspondence, printed material, hand written and typewritten manuscripts of books and articles, clippings, photographs, negatives, and glass slides, and an audio tape, dating chiefly from 1931-1959. Crum acquired the materials over the course of his career as a professor of Biblical literature who had interests in African American history, psychology, race relations, and recent Methodist church history. His major area of research was the Gullah communities of Edisto and St. Helena, two of the South Carolina Sea Islands, with the bulk of work here dating from the 1930s; the result of the research was Gullah, published by Duke University Press in 1940.
Other areas of interest reflected in the papers are moral education, pastoral counseling, and religious pageantry. Crum's concern with Christianity and race relations is shown by his participation in cooperative efforts in education, and in the teaching of one of the first Black studies courses in the South (1954).
Also included in the papers are photographs from the Sea Islands, from Junaluska, N.C., and more personal images of family, children, and relating to the Washington Duke family in Durham, N.C.
African American churches; African Americans -- Sea Islands; African Americans -- Study and teaching; Gullahs; Islands -- South Carolina; Race relations -- Religious aspects; Religion -- Study and teaching; Segregation -- Southern States; Edisto Island (S.C.); Lake Junaluska (N.C.) -- Photographs; Sea Islands; Sea Islands Creole dialect; Sea Islands -- Photographs; St. Helena Island (S.C.); Lantern slides; Photographs; Cellulose nitrate film; Clippings (information artifacts); Negatives (photographs); Sound recordings; Methodist Episcopal Church, South; Duke University. Department of Religion; Duke University -- Faculty; Crum, Mason, b. 1887; Duke family -- Photographs
- Correspondence, 1889-1974, undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of personal and family letters; correspondence from Crum's days as a salesman, and correspondence relating to his activities as an educator and Methodist layman. Among the last is material relating to boys' camps, Methodist Church activities, the Y.M.C.A., letters to publishers, Lake Junaluska Summer School, and Crum's other interests and activities.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged chronologically, with a sub-series, Subject Correspondence, 1926-1971, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Correspondence, 1889-1937 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1944 (Box 2, Folder 6-10)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1951 (Box 3, Folder 11-15)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1967 (Box 4, Folder 16-20)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Subject Correspondence
    The sub-series, Subject Correspondence, consists of one box with material on: Camp Junaluska for Boys, 1926-1930; Chi Phi fraternity, 1948-1958; correspondence and reviews concerning the publication of Gullah; Lake Junaluska properties, 1949-1958; North Carolina College Teachers of Religion, 1938-1949; correspondence and reactions to his article, A Southerner Looks at Segregation (1954), which was published in The Christian Advocate, November 11, 1954; correspondence concerning cooperative efforts in race relations, 1936-1954. This last contains material from state, college and university, and denominational agencies concerned with bettering race relations. Among the organizations represented are the Division of Cooperation in Education and Race Relations of the North Carolina Dept. of Public Instruction, the University of North Carolina, the Dept. of Race Relations of the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America, and Duke University. Committee work, conferences, and other activities are represented in the file.
    - Camp Junaluska for Boys, 1926-1930 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Chi Phi fraternity, 1908, 1943-1958 (Box 4, Folder 24, Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Gullah publication, 1938-1971 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Lake Junaluska, 1949-1958 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - North Carolina College Teachers of Religion, 1938-1949 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Race relations, 1936-1954 (Box 5, Folder 29-30)
    - A Southerner Looks at Segregation article, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Subject files, 1885-1957, undated
  Printed materials, research notes, a diary and cashbook, and other materials. Personal records include Crum's vitae and genealogy, a diary he kept while at Harvard, and a cashbook (1885-1895) from his father's store in Orangeburg County. Academic materials consist of class rolls, 1930- 1957, course materials, including test materials and clippings concerning his course on Black History, and several student papers. Also in the subject files are records and programs for the Lake Junaluska Assembly, research notes on various topics, including race relations and the Gullah communities, and a bibliography on Black History.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Bibliography of the Negro, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Family genealogical and Mason Crum biographical information, 1939-1961 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Cashbook, 1885-1895 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Certificates and awards, 1957, 1969 (Box 17, Folder 130)
  - Cherokee history: Indian Gap Trail, Park Service paper, 1942-1949 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Clippings and reprints, 1951-1954 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Personal clippings, 1935-1957 (Box 6, Folder 37-38)
  - Columbia College, undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Courses
    - Educational Psychology, 1929 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Religion 185, "Negro Americans", 1954-1956 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Religion 169-170, 1932-1933 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Test material, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Diary from year at Harvard University, 1912 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Lake Junaluska
    - Assembly Programs, 1913-1929 (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Assembly Programs, 1930-1951 (Box 7, Folder 46-47)
    - Camps, 1927-1931 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Conferences, 1917-1953 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Land management, Orangeville County, S.C., 1928-1948 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Miscellaneous documents, 1921-1960 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Miscellaneous published material (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Miscellaneous records, 1894-1930 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Pastor's School, 1926-1934 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Personal and worship notes, reflection on call to ministry, 1909-1911, undated (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Printed material: Workbook Manual for Marriage and the Family by John Harvey Furbay, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Recommendations for employment [written by others about Mason Crum], 1909-1913 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Race relations (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Religio-Psychiatric Clinic, 1957-1963 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Religious education, 1929-1949 (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Study of Religion in the Colleges of N.C., circa 1937 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Sermon notes, 1915-1920 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - University of South Carolina, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Teaching (Box 8, Folder 64)
- Writings, 1911-1967, undated
  Hand- and typewritten manuscripts, notebooks, bound volumes, together with research notes, for published and unpublished books and articles. Not included are the Guide to Religious Pageantry (published in 1923) and The Project Method in Religion (Ph.D. thesis, University of South Carolina, 1924). Works represented are: 1) Autobiography, tentatively titled The Young Bee Makes the Honeycomb, [1959-1960]. 2) A Boy's Life of Albert Schweitzer, undated 3) Character Building, various dates 4) Cherokee Legends of the Great Smokey Mountains, [1954-1962] 5) Child Development, writings on, various dates 6) Childhood and Character, [1929] 7) College term papers, Harvard, [1911-1912]. 8) Counseling College Students, [1930-1967]. 9) Doorways of Duke, [1950], on Duke architecture. 10) Duke University and the Things of the Spirit, undated 11) Family counseling, writings on, various dates. 12) Fiction, unpublished short stories, various dates. 13) Gullah. Duke University Press, 1940. Bound typescript and personal copy. 14) History of the Southern Christian Advocate, undated The Advocate is a South Carolina Methodist publication. 15) Life Among the Gullah Negroes, undated 16) Life and Times of Washington Duke, undated 17) A Little Girl Named Maggie, [1953, how Maggie Valley, N.C. got its name.] 18) Miscellaneous articles 19) The Negro in the Methodist Church. The Board of Missions and the Church Extension, The Methodist Church, 1951. Bound copy inscribed to Dr. and Mrs. Gross. 20) A Negro Story Nobody Knows: When Negro Methodists sat in Southern Churches (tentative title), undated [on the pre-Civil War period] 21) Writings on Religion 22) A Southerner Looks at Segregation, 1955 (written in response to the Supreme Court decision Brown v. Board of Education) 23) Speaking of Boys, undated (Chapter 3) 24) The Story of Lake Junaluska, 1950, and Chief Junaluska. 25) Where Your Hillbilly Music Comes From, undated
  - Autobiography
    - First draft, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 65-66)
    - The Young Bee Makes the Honeycomb: The Short and Simple Annals of a College Professor, Chapters 1-20, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 67-68)
  - A Boy's Life of Albert Schweitzer (Box 9, Folder 69)
  - Character Building (Box 9, Folder 70-71)
  - Cherokee Indians, 1953-1954 (Box 10, Folder 72-73)
  - Cherokee Legends of the Great Smokey Mountains, 1954-1962 (Box 10, Folder 74)
  - Cherokee Indian legends, undated (Box 10, Folder 75)
  - Child development, undated (Box 10, Folder 76)
  - Childhood and character, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 77-78)
  - College term papers, Harvard, 1911-1912 (Box 11, Folder 79-80)
  - Counseling college students, 1930-1967 (Box 11, Folder 81)
  - Doorways of Duke, 1950 (Box 11, Folder 82)
  - Duke University and things of the spirit, undated (Box 11, Folder 83)
  - Family counseling, 1919-1953 (Box 11, Folder 84)
  - Fiction, undated (Box 11, Folder 85)
  - Gullah: Negro Life in the Carolina Sea Islands, 1940
    - Research notes, Gullah life and visit to a Negro Church in Durham (Box 12, Folder 86)
    - Gullah: Negro Life in the Carolina Sea Islands. Durham, N.C.: Duke University Press, 1940., Signed by the author on the front fly-leaf and on the title page. (Box 12, Folder 87)
    - Typed manuscript draft, Chapters 1-14, undated (Box 12, Folder 88-89)
    - Dust jacket, Duke University Press, 1940 (Box 13, Folder 90)
  - History of the Southern Christian Advocate, undated (Box 13, Folder 91)
  - Life Among Gullah Negroes (Box 13, Folder 92)
  - Life and Times of Washington Duke (Box 13, Folder 93-98)
  - A Little Girl Named Maggie or Maggie Valley: A True Story from a Great Smoky Mountain Region, 1953 (Box 14, Folder 99)
  - A Little Girl Named Maggie: Paintings, 1953 (Box 17, Folder 131)
  - The Negro in the Methodist Church. New York: Board of Missions and Church Extension, The Methodist Church, circa 1951; Inscribed by the author on the title page: "To: Dr. Paul Gross and Mrs. Gross from Mason Crum". (Box 14, Folder 100)
  - A Negro History Nobody Knows
    - A Negro History Nobody Knows; When Negro Methodists Sat in Southern Churches, holograph manuscripts, undated (Box 14, Folder 101-102)
    - A Negro Story Nobody Knows: The Forgotten Chapter in Southern History, holograph manuscript, 1944 (Box 14, Folder 103-104)
    - A Negro Story Nobody Knows, annotated typescript and photocopy (Box 15, Folder 108, Box 14, Folder 105-107)
  - Religion (Box 15, Folder 109)
  - A Southerner Looks at Segregation, 1955 (Box 15, Folder 110-111)
  - Speaking of Boys, Chapter 3 (Box 15, Folder 112)
  - The Story of Lake Junaluska, 1946 (Box 15, Folder 113-115)
  - Where Your Hillbilly Music Comes From (Box 15, Folder 116)
- Photographs
  This series includes a number of images of Sea Island Gullah community scenes and people, photographed by Mason Crum in about 1935-1936, as well as a few photographs of charcoal portraits done in the Sea Islands by Winold Reiss of St. Helen. These images include 61 10" x 13" black and white prints mounted on 15" x 20" boards and individually numbered; many of these are labeled and signed by Mason Crum. Also included in this group are 48 3" x 4" glass lantern slides, very few of which overlap with the mounted prints, as well as several prints. These images depict landscapes, portraits, buildings and activities in the Gullah communities on the islands of Edisto and St. Helena's.
  Personal photographs include a number of images of Mason Crum's family, including his ancestors, parents, sister, wife, children, as well as a former slave, Charles Baxter, and Mason Crum's childhood nurse, Julia Edwards. There are a large number of images of Lake Junaluska, including lake scenery, the Lake Junaluska Boys' Camp, groups of people, and houses, as well as surrounding areas in the Appalachian region of North Carolina. Also included are images of Mason Crum's classes at Duke and other schools; images from the "Doorways of Duke" article; images related to Washington Duke and the Duke family in Durham for "The Life and Times of Washington Duke"; clippings, an illustration, and a cover of World Outlook featuring Mason Crum and family; a number of other images identified and unidentified.
  Most of the images are photographic prints, mounted and unmounted. Also included are glass lantern slides, 35mm color slides, safety film negatives, and nitrate negatives. Nitrate negatives are closed to research.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Nitrate negatives are closed to use. Copies are available. Please contact the Rubenstein Library Research Services for assistance.
  - Gullah: Edisto and St. Helena Islands, 1934-1940
    - Edisto and St. Helena Islands: oversize prints, circa 1940, undated (Box 17, Folder 136)
    - Sea Island Images: mounted oversize prints 1-32, 1934-1935 (Box 18)
    - Sea Island Images: mounted oversize prints 33-61, 1934-1935 (Box 19)
    - Edisto and St. Helena Islands: glass lantern slides, circa 1936 (Box 21)
      Because of their vulnerability, it is preferable to use surrogate copies instead of original glass plate slides. Please contact the Rubenstein Library Research Services staff for assistance.
  - Personal photographs
    Nitrate negatives are closed to use; copies are available. Please contact the Rubenstein Library Research Services staff for assistance.
    - Family photographs: Charles Baxter, Julia Edwards, "Mom" Patti: prints, 1919-1941 (Box 16, Folder 117)
    - Family photographs: Charles Baxter: negatives (NITRATE), circa 1935 (Box 20, Image UA29020032-N-0001 - UA29020032-N-0004)
      Access Restrictions
    - Family photographs: Mason Crum and ancestors, parents, sister: prints, copy negative, 1908-1941, undated (Box 16, Folder 118)
    - Family photographs: Crum family home: oversize prints, 1905 (Box 17, Folder 132)
    - Family photographs: Mason and Katherine Crum and children: prints, 1919-1970 (Box 16, Folder 119)
    - Family photographs: Mason Crum and children: negatives (NITRATE), undated (Box 20, Image UA29020032-N-13 - UA29020032-N-26)
    - Family photographs: Mason Crum school photographs: oversize prints, 1902, 1908 (Box 17, Folder 133)
    - Family photographs: Mason Crum school photos: oversize prints, 1909-1910 (Box 17, Folder 134)
    - Family photographs: Crum family at home: mounted oversize print (Box 19)
    - Mason Crum teaching, non-Duke: prints, 1911-1923 (Box 16, Folder 120)
    - Mason Crum at Duke: prints, 1932-1957 (Box 16, Folder 121)
    - Lake Junaluska: prints, copy negatives, undated (Box 16, Folder 122-123)
    - Lake Junakuska: oversize prints, undated (Box 17, Folder 135)
    - Lake Junaluska: negatives (NITRATE), undated (Box 20, Image UA29020032-N-68 - UA29020032-N-71, Image UA29020032-N-27 - UA29020032-N-34)
    - Doorways of Duke: prints, undated (Box 16, Folder 124)
    - Doorways of Duke: negatives (NITRATE) (Box 20, Image UA29020032-N-35 - UA29020032-N-43)
    - Images related to Washington Duke and family, with notes: prints and copy prints, 1940, 1945, undated (Box 16, Folder 125-126)
    - Images related to Washington Duke and family: negatives (NITRATE), circa 1940-1945 (Box 20, Image UA29020032-N-05 - UA29020032-N-12)
    - "Homes of Garden Club Members, Neighbors": color slides, undated (Box 16, Folder 127)
    - Identified: other prints, 1903-1945, undated (Box 16, Folder 128)
    - Illustration, clipping, World Outlook covers, 1908, 1943, 1950, 1974, undated (Box 17, Folder 137)
    - Unidentified: prints. negatives, undated (Box 16, Folder 129)
    - Unidentified: negatives (NITRATE) (Box 20, Image UA29020032-N-44 - UA29020023-N-67)
- Audio tape, undated
  1 7" reel audio tape, Mason Crum performing "Cotton Field Ballads" said to be illustrative of a chapter in his autobiography on southern songs and ballads.
  Audio tapes are stored with the Sound Recordings collection.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  This recording has been transferred and is available on audio cassette.